Register of the Zimbabwean Subject Collection 1904-2008
Hoover Institution Archives
Zimbabwean subject collection,
1904-2008
XX788
8 manuscript boxes, 4 phonorecords, 3 phonotape cassettes (3.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Electronic bulletins, pamphlets, flyers, reports, government documents, press releases, other printed matter, and audiovisual materials, relating to revolutionary movements in Zimbabwe, especially the Zimbabwe African National Union and the Zimbabwe African People's Union, the history of Zimbabwe, and political, social and economic conditions in Zimbabwe.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives. An increment was added in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Electronic bulletins, pamphlets, flyers, reports, government documents, press releases, other printed matter, and audiovisual materials, relating to revolutionary movements in Zimbabwe, especially the Zimbabwe African National Union and the Zimbabwe African People's Union, the history of Zimbabwe, and political, social and economic conditions in Zimbabwe.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Zimbabwe African National Union.; Zimbabwe African People's Union.; Zimbabwe--History--1965-1980.; Phonorecords.; Phonotapes.; Videotapes
Collection Contents
- SUBJECT FILE, 1920-1995. (Box 1-4)
  Clippings, correspondence, fact sheet, flyers, government documents, leaflets, map, memoramda, newsletter, pamphlets, press briefing, press release, printed matter, serial issues, and speeches relating to economic, political and social conditions in Zimbabwe
- REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENTS, 1963-1995. (Box 4-5)
  Clippings, communiques, memoranda, newsletters, press release, printed matter, reports and speeches relating to revolutionary movements in Zimbabwe
- AUDIO-VISUAL FILE, 1965-1985. (Cassette cabinet; Record cabinet)
  3 phonotape cassettees and 4 phonorecords of Rhodesian Troopiesongs and speeches relating to Zimbabwe
- INCREMENTAL MATERIAL (Box 6-8)
Container List
See card catalog for increments that may have been received after February 1995
- SUBJECT FILE, 1920-1995
  - General (Box 1)
    - General
    - Clippings
  - Colonial era
  - Commonwealth Press Union
  - Culture
  - Economic policies
    - General
    - Agriculture
    - Beira Corridor
    - Sanctions
  - Education
    - General
    - Univeristy of Zimbabwe (Box 2)
  - Elections
    - General
    - 1980
  - Foreign relations
    - General
    - Botswana
    - Far East
    - Malawi
    - Non-aligned nations
    - Romania
    - Tanzania
    - United Kingdom
    - United States
  - Health
    - General
    - Acquired Immune Deficiency System (AIDS)
  - Hutchinson, John
  - International support groups
    - General
    - American Friends of Rhodesia
  - Mapfumo, Thomas
  - Matabeleland Rebellion, 1896-1897
  - National parks and wildlife management
  - Political and religious organizations
    - Catholic Commission for Justice and Peace in Zimbabwe
    - Federation of the Covenant People (Box 3)
    - Jesuit Missions
    - Justice for Rhodesia Campaign
    - National Unifying Force
    - Rhodesia Christian Group
    - United Reform Organization
    - Women for Rhodesia
  - Political parties
    - General
    - Central African Party
    - Centre Party
    - Conservative Alliance Zimbabwe
    - National Democratic Party
    - Rhodesian Action Party
    - Rhodesian Front
    - Rhodesian National Party
    - United African National Council of Zimbabwe
      - General
      - Constitutional conference, 1976
      - Press release, statements, newsletters and reports
      - Speeches
        - Muzorewa, Bishop Abel
        - Razemba, Elton
    - Zimbabwe Congress Party
    - Zimbabwe United People's Organization
  - Politics and government
    - General
    - Independence
  - Religion
  - Rhodesian Information Office (Box 4)
  - Rhodesian Ministry of Defense
  - Rhodesian Ministry of Information
  - "Rho-Plan 60"
  - Tourism
  - Women
- REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENTS, 1963-1995
  - General (Box 4)
  - Front for the Liberation of Zimbabwe (FROLIZI)
  - Zimbabwe African National Union (ZANU)
    - General
    - Clippings
    - Communiques and press releases
    - Newsletters
    - Speeches and statements by Rober Mugabe
  - Zimbabwe African People's Union (ZAPU)
    - General
    - Central Committee
    - International support groups (Box 5)
      - Liberation Support Movement
      - World Federation of Democratic Youth
    - Newsletters, memoranda and reports
    - Publications
    - Speeches by Joshua Nkomo
- AUDIO-VISUAL FILE, 1965-1985
  - Phonotape cassettes (Cassette-cabinet Cassette cabinet)
    - "All 49 Original Rhodesian Troopiesongs," 1984. Two cassettes.
    - "Independence." Speeches by Ian Smith and Harold Wilson, 1965-1966
  - Phonorecords (Record-cabinet Record cabinet)
    - "All 49 Original Rhodesian Troopiesongs," 1984
    - "Chimurenga Singles, 1976-1980," 1985
    - "Wisdom of Years," 1976. Two phonorecords
- Incremental Materials (Box 6-8)
  A digital use copy of the DVD (box 8) containing the video "The Power of Love" (duration 24:03, copyright Lois Davis) is available in the reading room. The video is about the activities of Women of Zimbabwe Arise (WOZA) and its nonviolent approach to mobilizing people for social justice in Zimbabwe. Interviews of Zimbabweans are interspersed with footage of meetings, street scenes, demonstrations, etc. in Zimbabwe; and some still photographs. The video was created around the time of 2008 elections in Zimbabwe. Narrated in English, with English subtitles for interviews of Zimbabweans.
  The rest of this addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described. Contact us at hooverarchivesinfo@stanford.edu